Guide to the Steffi Domike Papers, 1946-2009 AIS.1997.20
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Steffi Domike Papers
1946-2007
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Domike, Steffi
AIS.1997.20
77.17 Linear Feet (includes 721 video cassettes, 129 cassette tapes, 72 film reels, 1 oversize box and 1 tube)
Steffi Ronder Domike worked as an electrician's assistant at Clairton Coke Works where she belonged to the United Steelworkers of America (USWA) Local 1557 and was a union and equal rights activist. After being laid off in 1982 during the wave of steelworker lay offs in the Monongahela Valley, she became a filmmaker and went on to document steel industry labor movements of the Pittsburgh area, including the 1892 Homestead Strike and the community impact of the closing of U.S. Steel's National Duquesne Works in the 1980s. This collection contains correspondence, newsletters, minutes, reports, and articles about steelworker local unions and the steel industry during the 1970s and 1980s. Materials relating to the oral history project Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport and the documentary film/book The River Ran Red include grant proposals, research articles, publicity articles, and archival images. Production films from Women of Steel and The River Ran Red are also included. Additional materials were processed and added to the collection in October of 2011 which include materials relating to the various productions Domike was involved in as a producer and/or director. Also included are materials that document Domike's exhibits and installations, her involvement in the Battle of Homestead Foundation, and SubRosa, as well as research materials.
Biography
Steffi Domike spent most of her early years in Santiago, Chile while her father worked for the United Nations. After returning to the United States, she eventually moved to the Pittsburgh area to work as an electrician's apprentice at United States Steel's Clairton Coke Works. During her tenure there, she emerged as an active member of USWA Local 1557 and represented the local in the USWA District 15 Civil Rights Committee. In 1979, she ran for recording secretary of the local. Domike was involved in Steelworkers Stand Up, a newsletter which described problems and spread notice of important union events at the Clairton Coke Works and other mills. She also played an active role in women's rights within the steel industry by contributing to Women of Steel newsletters and organizing meetings prior to the 1976 USWA International Constitutional Convention in which amendments regarding union women's rights were to be presented. After being laid off in 1982 with thousands of other steelworkers, Domike joined the Mon Valley Unemployed Steelworkers Committee ("Steelworkers" was later removed) and their St. Peter's Church Food Bank, located in McKeesport. She also enrolled in the Art Institute of Pittsburgh and Pittsburgh Filmmakers to study filmmaking. With three other women from the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee (MVUC), Domike used student interviewers to create an oral history project and book called Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport which compared the decline of the steel industry in the 1980s with the Great Depression of the 1930s.
Domike and three other MVUC committee members also produced Women of Steel, an award-winning 1985 documentary about the lives of three women steelworkers. Other film and television projects include: a film about three women who choose to become single mothers, Life without Father, Out of this Furnace: A Walking Tour of Thomas Bell's Novel, an exposé of the Atlantic coastal community of Nicaragua called Nicarribe, the instructional program, Win-Win Bargaining, and the WQED TV series Labor's Corner. Probably her most notable film is the 1992 documentary The River Ran Red. Co-produced with Nicole Fauteux, this film documents the conflict between the steelworkers and the Carnegie Steel Company and Pinkerton Guards at Homestead in 1892. The film is complemented by a collection of source readings, compiled by Domike and Fauteux, with the same title.
Domike continues to work as an artist and activist and has created a board game with Lisa Freeland which takes a critical look at the Patriot Act. She was also part of an interactive history documentary called Terminal Time, and has created various works of art on feminist, environmentalist, and labor themes.
Scope and Content Notes
These files reflect Steffi Domike's participation in United Steelworkers of America Local 1557 while working as an electrician's apprentice at U.S. Steel's Clairton Coke Works. They also document her activities after being laid off in 1982. She worked with the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee and as a filmmaker and producer. Some of the collection's manuscript materials include correspondence, newsletters, minutes, reports, and articles about local steelworkers unions, rank and file movements, and the international steelworkers union during the 1970s and 1980s. Materials relating to the oral history project Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport and the documentary film/book The River Ran Red include grant proposals, research articles, publicity articles, archival images, scripts, artwork, and promotional materials. A large array of films and shows produced or written by Domike make up the larger part of this collection. There are film reels, videos, photographs, negatives, and slides pertaining to local labor issues and the production of works like Women of Steel and The River Ran Red. There are also audio cassettes of interviews and audio tracks used in the production of her works.
Significant changes have been made to the organization of the collection as a result of accruals in 2010 and 2011. These changes may affect previously cited material, particularly in series pertaining to audio visual material and The River Ran Red.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into 14 series:
Series I. The USX Clairton Coke Works, 1946-1979
Series II. Women of Steel
Series III. The State of the Steel Industry, 1975-1979
Series IV. Edward Sadlowski Campaign, 1976-1978
Series V. Mon Valley Food Bank, 1982-1983
Series VI. Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport, Oral History Project
Series VII. The River Ran Red
Series VIII. Committees, Rallies, and Strikes, 1977-1984
Series IX. Audio/Visual Materials
Series X. Personal Material, 1982-2009
Series XI. Production Materials, 1986-1999
Series XII. Projects, 1983-2006
Series XIII. Research Materials, 1973-2009
Series XIV. Oversize Materials, 1912-2000
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Additional gift made on March 4, 2010.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Steffi Domike on June 9, 1997.
Previous Citation
Steffi Domike Papers, 1946-2009, AIS.1997.20, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
The files relating to Domike's participation in labor unions and her files relating to filmmaking were originally separated into two different collections. This collection, AIS.1997.20, reflects the unification of collections AIS.1997.20 and parts of AIS.1984.20. This collection has also been cited as Papers of Steffi Domike, 1946-1994, ue199720, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Existence and Location of Originals note
In the course of researching for The River Ran Red, Domike and Fauteux acquired photocopies of many articles and newspapers, as well as reproductions of photographs, from various other repositories including the Library of Congress, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, and the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh.
Related Material
Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport prepared by the McKeesport Oral History Project, Mon Valley Unemployed Committee is available at the Archives Service Center under call number F159 M2C72 1983.
Records of the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, AIS.2002.02, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
A microfilm reel from the former collection AIS.1984.20 contains press releases and clippings regarding McKeesport's economic struggles in the 1980s.
Filmmakers; Photographs; Newsletters; Minutes (Administrative records); Clairton (Pa.); Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Industrial relations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Labor disputes -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Labor movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Strikes and lockouts -- Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Personal papers; Women labor leaders -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Labor; Woman labor union members -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Women; Women in the labor movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Women motion picture producers and directors; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Allegheny County (Pa.); Betacam (TM); Gender mainstreaming -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsurgh Region; Sex discrimination against women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Reproductive rights -- United States; Film (Performing arts); Slides (Photographs); Audiocassettes; Videotapes; Video recordings (physical artifacts); United Steel Workers Association; Steel Workers Organizing Committee (U.S.); Battle of Homestead Foundation (Pa.); Pittsburgh Teachers Institute (Pa.); Summer Youth Employment and Training Program (U.S.); Domike, Steffi; Mon-Valley Unemployed Committee; Pittsburgh Film-Makers Inc.; Sadlowski, Edward; Steel Valley Authority of the Mon Valley; United States Steel Corporation. Clairton Works; United Steelworkers of America. Local 1557 (Clairton, Pa.)
- USX Clairton Coke Works, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The USX Clairton Coke Works files contain documents regarding Domike's work as an active member of the USWA Local 1557 and as part of the Committee of Concerned Unionists (CCU). Documents in the collection regarding her involvement in the CCU include correspondence, pamphlets and information about environmental organizations, such as the Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP) and Enviro-SOS. Also included in this series are layout sheets and articles for the Clairton newsletter Steelworkers Stand Up, which described problems and announced important events within the steel industry, the USWA, and other unions. Information regarding Domike's candidacy for the office of Local 1557 recording secretary and grievances from the Clairton Works' wiregang dating from 1946-1979 are also present.
  - Committee of Concerned Unionists, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Control and Pollution, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GASP and Enviro-SOS, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Steelworkers Stand Up Layout Sheets, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter regarding 1557 Journal (Clairton) Article, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wiregang Grievances with Motor Inspectors, 1946-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - USWA Local 1557 Election, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Women of Steel, II.
  This series contains records about local and national union activities regarding women. These files include District 15's Civil Rights Committee records, labor women and trade news clippings, Women of Steel newsletters, information on the 1976 International USWA Constitutional Convention, and Domike's "Snappy Answers to Stupid Questions," a satirical pamphlet directed against the sexual harassment of women in the mills. Samplings of Domike's labor pins on various topics are also present.
  - Civil Rights Committee, District 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Labor Women and Trade Unions News Clippings (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women of Steel Newsletter, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Consent Decree and Equal Pay (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - International USWA Conference, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Snappy Answers to Stupid Questions" (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Labor Pins (Box 1, Folder 16)
- The State of Steel Industry, 1975-1979; III.
  The State of the Steel Industry series represents records from the national, as well as local union, levels. These records consist of magazine and news clippings about the steel industry, a list of United Steelworkers' Shops, and Rank and File Team newsletters from 1975-1976.
  - Magazines and News Clippings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - United Steel Workers Shops, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rank and File Team Newsletters, c.1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Edward Sadlowski Campaign, 1976-1979; IV.
  This series contains documents related to the campaign of Edward Sadlowski for the presidency of the United Steelworkers of America. These files include Sadlowski's platform and the platform of his opponent, Lloyd McBride, and publicity information which appeared in various steel union newsletters. Also present are the National Steelworkers Rank and File Committee Reports, election results, and press releases.
  - Steelworkers Stand Up Correspondence Regarding a Sadlowski Appearance (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Steelworker Union Articles (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sadlowski Publicity (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - McBride Publicity (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Local Union Articles Regarding Sadlowski (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Communist Party-United Steelworkers Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Steelworkers Rank and File Committee Report and Labor Today, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - S.M.A.R.T. (Steelworker Members Against Radical Takeover) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Union Coupler, Local Union 1531 Newsletter, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Steve Early's Steelworkers Reports on the Sadlowski Campaign, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1397 Rank & File Newsletter, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Steelworkers Voice, District 20, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Militant on Sadlowski, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Clairton Rank and File Voice, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Experimental Negotiations Agreement (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Local Newsletters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - District 15 Rank and File Minutes (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Steelworkers Stand-Up (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Fighting Times Clairton Local Rank and File Newsletter, November 1977-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Press Releases (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - USWA International Election Results, District 15 and Master Sheet by Districts, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - International Elections Results (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - USWA Iron On Logo (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Mon Valley Unemployed Committee and Food Bank, 1982-1983; V.
  This series contains records related to the Mon Valley Food Bank and reflect the joint efforts of the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee and St. Peter's Church in McKeesport, Pennsylvania to provide food assistance to laid-off local union members. While working with the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, Domike was responsible for the St. Peter's Church Food Bank's newsletters, which are included in this series along with minutes, correspondence, and press releases.
  - Newsletters, Minutes, Correspondence, and Member Lists (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport Oral History Project, 1983; VI.
  The Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport Oral History Project records consist of audio cassettes and transcripts, a bibliography, papers regarding oral history techniques, a Mon Valley Unemployed Committee slide show script about McKeesport, research, field questions, and photo essays. Interviews for the project were completed by students hired under a Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) grant. The goal of the grant was to talk to people who lived through the Great Depression or had personal experiences with the 1980s downturn of the steel industry in the Monongahela Valley.
  - Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport, Oral History Project Material, 1983; 1.
    - Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Oral History Techniques (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Conducting an Interview (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mon Valley Unemployment Committee Slideshow Script (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - First Pages of Book (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Slideshow (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Elizabeth Township Historical Society (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - List of Book Donations (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Flyers for Public Presentation (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Completed Legal Releases (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Office Inventory and Calender (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Supervisor's Time Sheets (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Student Interviews (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Supervisor Handbook (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Notes and Field Questions (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Research (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Receipts Incurred (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Handwritten Grant Proposals (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - McKeesport Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Mon-Valley Unemployed Committee Summer Youth Employment Oral History Project, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Photographs and Photo Essays (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Edited Interviews (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport, Oral History Project Interviews, 1983; 2.
    - Interview of Paul Edna Barnes (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Interview of Junious Brown (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Interview of Lois Brown (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Interview of Nick and Joanne Burton (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Interview of Samuel Buckman (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Interview of Arthur Cready, et al. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Interview of Bernadine Davis (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Interview of Phil DiRoca (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Interview of Rocky Doratio (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Interview of Linda Ganzak (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Interview of Dick Grace (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Interview of Percy Garland (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Interview of Andrew Jakomas (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Interview of Wilda Ketchum (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Interview of Oscar Lechman (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Interview of Peter Lupo (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Interview of Phil McGuigan (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Interview of Frank Muic (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Interview of Virginia Murray (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Interview of Joseph Odorcich (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Interview of Barney Oursler (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Interview of Marie Papula (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Interview of Rich Pompanio (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Interview of Reuben Sayles (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Interview of Tim Session (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Interview of Fred Stipkovitz (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Interview of Jackie Sutrice (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Interview of Michael Tokarsly (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Interview of Tony Tomko (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Interview of George Vukmanic (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Interview of Anna May Williams (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Crashin' Out: Hard Times in McKeesport, Interview Cassettes, 3.
    - Interview of Paul Edna Barnes (Box 3, Cassette 1)
    - Interview of Junious Brown (Box 3, Cassette 2)
    - Interview of Lois Brown (Box 3, Cassette 3)
    - Interview of Nick and Joanne Burton (Box 3, Cassette 4)
    - Interview of Samuel Buckman (Box 3, Cassette 5)
    - Interview of Arthur Cready, et al. (Box 3, Cassette 6)
    - Interview of Bernadine Davis (Box 3, Cassette 7)
    - Interview of Phil DiRoca (Box 3, Cassette 8)
    - Interview of Rocky Doratio (Box 3, Cassette 9)
    - Interview of Linda Ganzak (Box 3, Cassette 10)
    - Interview of Dick Grace (Box 3, Cassette 11)
    - Interview of Percy Garland (Box 3, Cassette 12)
    - Interview of Andrew Jakomas (Box 3, Cassette 13)
    - Interview of Wilda Ketchum (Box 3, Cassette 14)
    - Interview of Oscar Lechman (Box 3, Cassette 15)
    - Interview of Peter Lupo (Box 3, Cassette 16)
    - Interview of Phil McGuigan (Box 3, Cassette 17)
    - Interview of Frank Muic (Box 3, Cassette 18)
    - Interview of Virginia Murray (Box 3, Cassette 19)
    - Interview of Joseph Odorcich (Box 3, Cassette 20)
    - Interview of Barney Oursler (Box 3, Cassette 21)
    - Interview of Marie Papula (Box 3, Cassette 22)
    - Interview of Rich Pompanio (Box 3, Cassette 23)
    - Interview of Reuben Sayles (Box 3, Cassette 24)
    - Interview of Tim Session (Box 3, Cassette 25)
    - Interview of Fred Stipkovitz (Box 3, Cassette 26)
    - Interview of Jackie Sutrice (Box 3, Cassette 27)
    - Interview of Michael Tokarsly (Box 3, Cassette 28)
    - Interview of Tony Tomko (Box 3, Cassette 29)
    - Interview of George Vukmanic (Box 3, Cassette 30)
    - Interview of Anna May Williams (Box 3, Cassette 31)
- The River Ran Red, VII.
  This series contains five subseries relating to Domike's work as the film's co-producer. Topics include funding, movie production, research materials, the film premiere, and book material.
  - Funding, 1.
    This subseries details the fundraising efforts for The River Ran Red, including applications to such granting agencies as the Pennsylvania Humanties Council, correspondence with potential donors and correspondence with several Pennsylvania legislators regarding their recommendation of the film for a state legislative initiative led by the Department of Community Affairs to bring grant money to the project. Project budgets and financial information documenting Mon Valley Media's non-profit eligibility are also present.
    - Legal Documents Regarding Made in the USA Productions, 1975-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Legal Correspondence from Elsa Rassbach, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Post Production and Grant Reports (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Mini-Grant, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Pittsburgh Filmmakers Auditor's Report and Budget, 1990-91 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Matching Funds, Checks and Donor Certification Forms, March 24, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Gifts, October, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Guidelines and Forms to be Submitted, October, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Christmas Party Fundraiser, December 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Reports, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Pennsylvania Humanities Council Grant Application, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - USWA Contributions, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Representative Chris McNally and the State Legislative Initiative Grant, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Senator Mike Dawida and the State Legislative Initiative, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Representative David Levdansky and the State Legislative Initiative, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Representative William Deweese and the State Legislative Initiative, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - American Income Life Insurance Co., 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Maurice Falk Medical Foundation, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Fundraising Appeals, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Pittsburgh Foundation, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Mon Valley Media Budgets, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Pennsylvania AFL-CIO, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission Grant Application, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Philadelphia American Federation of Teachers, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Canadian Autoworkers Union, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Carpenters District Council, Secretary/Treasurer Robert Argentine, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Communication Workers of America, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Henderson and Goldberg, P.C., 1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Jubilierer, Pass and Intrieri, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Pittsburgh Firefighters Local #1, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Teamsters, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Steel Industry Heritage Corporation, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Service Employees International Union, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Blue Cross of Western Pennsylvania, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Caroselli, Spagnolli, and Beachler, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 37)